<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Reach Beyond Grasp</title><link>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/</link><description>Personal Blog</description><atom:link href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/rss.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2014 11:21:32 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Walking in Wonderland - Trekking across the frozen Chadar</title><link>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/walking-in-wonderland-trekking-across-the-frozen-chadar.html</link><dc:creator>Raja Selvaraj</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;On no other trek could I have truthfully said that I was struck by a sense of wonder every time I looked up and around. We seemed to be walking and living in wonderland. It was much later, after seeing the reactions of others to the pictures that I realised that this was a near universal feeling, not something limited to me. Perhaps it was the simplicity of the landscape - ice, green waters, blue skies and brown cliffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/walking-in-wonderland-trekking-across-the-frozen-chadar.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (4 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>trek</category><guid>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/walking-in-wonderland-trekking-across-the-frozen-chadar.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2014 12:47:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Using wfdbtools</title><link>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/using-wfdbtools.html</link><dc:creator>Raja Selvaraj</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/RajaS/ecgtk/blob/master/ecgtk/wfdbtools.py"&gt;wfdbtools&lt;/a&gt;  is a pure python module for accessing and using the waveform data in &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.physionet.org/physiobank/"&gt;Physiobank&lt;/a&gt;. Provides rdsamp and rdann which are the python equivalents of the wfdb applications of similar names. A deliberate attempt is made to try to keep names and usage similar to the original wfdb applications for simplicity of use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/using-wfdbtools.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>code</category><guid>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/using-wfdbtools.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2013 12:31:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Kurangani to Top Station</title><link>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/kurangani-to-top-station.html</link><dc:creator>Raja Selvaraj</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The promised easy route down from Top Station was slowly turning nightmarish. For more than two hours we were following our guides through dense forest, with no trail, pushing away thorns, trying unsuccessfully to avoid the stinging nettles, repeatedly getting feet entangled in vine that proved much stronger than it looked, as we slid down the slopes and somehow managed to negotiate our way across a steep slope with sparse footholds, a slip from which would have plunged us onto the rocky walls of a stream far below. We were catching our breath in a clearing when the guide casually mentioned that the dead rotting leaves all around us could harbour king cobras. Some how, at that moment, with everything else, it did not seem to matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/kurangani-to-top-station.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (3 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>trek</category><guid>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/kurangani-to-top-station.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Oct 2012 12:20:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A month with Sublime Text</title><link>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/a-month-with-sublime-text.html</link><dc:creator>Raja Selvaraj</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don't write code for a living, still the amount of time I spend doing it makes me value a good editor. Like any decent programmer I am picky about what I use and biased towards what I prefer. Over the years, I have tried out a few different editors, notably gedit, geany, SPE, Komodo edit, Vim and Emacs. With patience and persistence, I think anyone will ultimately find the answer in Vi(m) or Emacs. For me it was Emacs that clicked and since the last 4 years or so, I have not really felt the need to try out another editor. With all the noise about Sublime Text, I thought it was time to give it a whirl, especially with the release of version 2, especially since some of the things in my current emacs setup were broken after the upgrade to Emacs 24. I used Sublime Text for about a month and these are some of my impressions -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/a-month-with-sublime-text.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (4 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>code</category><guid>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/a-month-with-sublime-text.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 31 Jul 2012 12:15:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Install Mendeley plugin for Libreoffice</title><link>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/install-mendeley-plugin-for-libreoffice.html</link><dc:creator>Raja Selvaraj</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;OK, I struggled with this for half an hour, so just to document the solution. On my new laptop with Ubuntu 12.04 and Libreoffice 3.5, I installed &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mendeley.com/"&gt;Mendeley&lt;/a&gt; with the deb package from the website. Installation went well, but when trying to install the openoffice plugin, it first complained it could not find unopkg. After some time I found that this was now located at /usr/lib/libreoffice/program/. So I pointed Mendeleydesktop towards this and now it ended with a warning that 'Couldn't Install OpenOffice Plugin The OpenOffice unopkg utility gave the following output:'. I read about manually installing the oxt which is at '/opt/mendeleydesktop/share/mendeleydesktop/openOfficePlugin/Mendeley-1.5.2.oxt' and opened the extension manager at libreoffice when I found that the Mendeley plugin is already installed. So, all I had to was restart Libreoffice and the Mendeley toolbar was now available.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>tech</category><guid>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/install-mendeley-plugin-for-libreoffice.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 May 2012 12:09:28 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>