<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Reach Beyond Grasp (tech)</title><link>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/categories/tech.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2014 11:21:32 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Install Mendeley plugin for Libreoffice</title><link>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/install-mendeley-plugin-for-libreoffice.html</link><dc:creator>Raja Selvaraj</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;OK, I struggled with this for half an hour, so just to document the solution. On my new laptop with Ubuntu 12.04 and Libreoffice 3.5, I installed &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mendeley.com/"&gt;Mendeley&lt;/a&gt; with the deb package from the website. Installation went well, but when trying to install the openoffice plugin, it first complained it could not find unopkg. After some time I found that this was now located at /usr/lib/libreoffice/program/. So I pointed Mendeleydesktop towards this and now it ended with a warning that 'Couldn't Install OpenOffice Plugin The OpenOffice unopkg utility gave the following output:'. I read about manually installing the oxt which is at '/opt/mendeleydesktop/share/mendeleydesktop/openOfficePlugin/Mendeley-1.5.2.oxt' and opened the extension manager at libreoffice when I found that the Mendeley plugin is already installed. So, all I had to was restart Libreoffice and the Mendeley toolbar was now available.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>tech</category><guid>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/install-mendeley-plugin-for-libreoffice.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 May 2012 12:09:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Linux on Thinkpad x220</title><link>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/linux-on-thinkpad-x220.html</link><dc:creator>Raja Selvaraj</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I bought a Lenovo Thinkpad X 220 recently. This is my third thinkpad, the previous ones being an X40 (stolen) and an X61s (showing signs of wear and tear after 4 years of heavy use). Overall, there is nothing to disappoint a thinkpad fan with the fantastic keyboard and solid build as expected. The differences are a wider screen (mixed feeling about this, the width makes it easier to code with a split screen, but the loss of height needs some getting used to), a trackpad (which I don't use much) and some additional media buttons (again, not important for me). The screen is thinner and lighter and along with an SSD makes the system lighter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/linux-on-thinkpad-x220.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>tech</category><guid>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/linux-on-thinkpad-x220.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 18 May 2012 11:32:36 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>