<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Reach Beyond Grasp (trek)</title><link>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/categories/trek.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2014 11:21:32 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Walking in Wonderland - Trekking across the frozen Chadar</title><link>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/walking-in-wonderland-trekking-across-the-frozen-chadar.html</link><dc:creator>Raja Selvaraj</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;On no other trek could I have truthfully said that I was struck by a sense of wonder every time I looked up and around. We seemed to be walking and living in wonderland. It was much later, after seeing the reactions of others to the pictures that I realised that this was a near universal feeling, not something limited to me. Perhaps it was the simplicity of the landscape - ice, green waters, blue skies and brown cliffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/walking-in-wonderland-trekking-across-the-frozen-chadar.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (4 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>trek</category><guid>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/walking-in-wonderland-trekking-across-the-frozen-chadar.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2014 12:47:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Kurangani to Top Station</title><link>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/kurangani-to-top-station.html</link><dc:creator>Raja Selvaraj</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The promised easy route down from Top Station was slowly turning nightmarish. For more than two hours we were following our guides through dense forest, with no trail, pushing away thorns, trying unsuccessfully to avoid the stinging nettles, repeatedly getting feet entangled in vine that proved much stronger than it looked, as we slid down the slopes and somehow managed to negotiate our way across a steep slope with sparse footholds, a slip from which would have plunged us onto the rocky walls of a stream far below. We were catching our breath in a clearing when the guide casually mentioned that the dead rotting leaves all around us could harbour king cobras. Some how, at that moment, with everything else, it did not seem to matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/kurangani-to-top-station.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (3 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>trek</category><guid>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/kurangani-to-top-station.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Oct 2012 12:20:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Bali Pass via Dehradun</title><link>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/bali-pass-via-dehradun.html</link><dc:creator>Raja Selvaraj</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;If I had my life to live over...&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;I would go more places.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;I would climb more mountains and swim more rivers...&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;- Don Harold&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/bali-pass-via-dehradun.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (11 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>trek</category><guid>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/bali-pass-via-dehradun.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2012 11:43:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Kumbakarai to Kodaikanal</title><link>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/kumbakarai-to-kodaikanal.html</link><dc:creator>Raja Selvaraj</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;img alt="On the way" class="align-right" src="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/img/on_the_way.jpg" style="width: 400px;"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a decision made over just a couple of days. A weekend trek to help prepare for the big one in the Himalayas that lay ahead in May. We learnt about this route from Kumbakarai falls to Kodaikanal which seemed to be [relatively well documented][1] and decided on it. Prasanna, Vishravars and Arun drove from Chennai and picked me up in Tindivanam. After a dinner of tasty idlis at Prasanna's place, we proceeded towards Dindigul. From Dindigul, we traveled to Periakulam and on towards the falls. Some distance before entering the Kumbakarai main road, we decided to catch some sleep by the roadside. Lying down at 3.30 am under a tree near a temple, it seemed idyllic until a squadron of marauding mosquitoes found us. We managed to sleep a little by crawling into the sleeping bags. We were back on the road at 5.30, had some idlis (again!) in Kumbakarai and were at the falls by 7.30 am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/kumbakarai-to-kodaikanal.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (3 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>trek</category><guid>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/posts/kumbakarai-to-kodaikanal.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2012 11:01:54 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>