<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Reach Beyond Grasp</title><link href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/</id><updated>2016-12-12T00:00:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Looking back</title><link href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/looking-back.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-12T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-12-12T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Raja Selvaraj</name></author><id>tag:rajaselvaraj.co.in,2016-12-12:/looking-back.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Milestones are to stop and look back on the road travelled. As the year ends, I am approaching the completion …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Milestones are to stop and look back on the road travelled. As the year ends, I am approaching the completion of seven years as an independent consultant electrophysiologist. I also recently completed 1000 device implants and 1000 electrophysiology&amp;nbsp;procedures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset right' src='/images/poster1.png' title='7 years' width='400px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uppermost is a feeling of satisfaction with how things have shaped up. These years have been a vindication of my decision to join and work at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JIPMER&lt;/span&gt;. But there are other, more important things that I think summarise this period and what I have learnt from&amp;nbsp;it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Documenting the journey - Importance of maintaining&amp;nbsp;records&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the beginning I have made all attempts to document all details of the interventional procedures and the follow ups. While this was cumbersome at times (not satisfied with what is available, I wrote the software myself, iterating through multiple versions over time), the benefits are undeniable. Having accurate data enables you to look back at your work objectively and quantitatively. It allows you to measure outcomes and compare them to established standards, which gives lot of confidence when judging the quality of your work. In any field, measuring your past performances gives you a feedback loop to help improve in the&amp;nbsp;future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset right' src='/images/poster2.png' title='KPI' width='400px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key performance indicators are are now well recognized as measurable indices of quality of work. Acute ablation success rates are easy to measure objectively and well reported from different centers. Since &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AV&lt;/span&gt; nodal reentrant tachycardia (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AVNRT&lt;/span&gt;) is the commonest arrhythmia requiring ablation, success rates for this procedure are reliably measured and can be compared with available information. For device implants, cephalic vein access rates has been mentioned as a marker of quality of an implanting center. This is again an easy to measure metric though skewed a little for us because there is a learning curve with a low successful access rate for each trainee during the initial period. Atrioventricular block and infections are the most dreaded complications associated with ablation procedures and device implants respectively and our numbers are well below reported rates. With the data behind me, I can say with confidence that our work in absolutely on par with the best in the&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t underestimate the learning&amp;nbsp;curve&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset right' src='/images/curve.png' title='Learning curve' width='600px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What the data also shows clearly, and which has been surprising for me, is the learning curve and how long it can be. Many measures, especially related to electrophysiology procedures, when plotted on a year-to-year basis, show a gradual and continuing improvement. This is evident for overall ablation success as seen above or success with specific procedures as seen below. At the end of 7 years and 1000 cases (closer to 1500 if all procedures I have participated in, instead of only those in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JIPMER&lt;/span&gt;, are counted), I think they are reaching the point where they should plateau or at least grow little. Of course, one can&amp;#8217;t over-interpret, given that this is data from just one person, but I think it shows that these procedures involve skills which take time to learn and establishes the importance of working in a place with a large volume, especially in the formative&amp;nbsp;years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset right' src='/images/poster4.png' title='Learning curve' width='400px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Publishing &amp;#8230; isn&amp;#8217;t only for the&amp;nbsp;credits&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset right' src='/images/poster5.png' title='Publications' width='400px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Publishing is usually seen as a necessary evil, something that is required for your next promotion, but is otherwise a drain on resources and a waste of time that can be spent doing clinical work. On the other hand, I see publishing as another way to establish the authenticity of the work you do, an acknowledgement that the quality of what you do is acceptable at an international level. Publishing from here is a little more difficult than it would have been from a reputed center abroad, especially for research articles. Support while preparing the paper is less, and there is a definite, perhaps unconscious bias from reviewers / editors when the paper comes from an institute in India. With shorter reports, the bias has been less or non-existent however. I am especially proud of the teaching rounds kind of reports that we have published in all the major &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EP&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;journals. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset right' src='/images/poster6.png' title='Publications' width='600px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Learning to&amp;nbsp;teach&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings me to one of the bits I have enjoyed the most in these years - teaching others. I have seen close to 20 cardiologists complete their training with us in these years and go on to work all across India. Teaching keeps you on your toes and, without doubt, is one of the best ways to learn. Teaching procedural skills without compromising patient safety of procedural efficiency while also allowing enough independence to build confidence to work independently requires the most exquisite balance. And looking at our results, I think we have maintained this&amp;nbsp;balance. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;But then finally it is about the&amp;nbsp;patients&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we were training in medicine, our teacher used to tell the patients &amp;#8220;Today you are helping us teach these students, in return they will help patients like you tomorrow.&amp;#8221; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JIPMER&lt;/span&gt; is an unique institute where most patients are still provided free treatment which helps the most disadvantaged sections. So each day I feel the satisfaction of repaying some of the old debts. Working here in this position, making a difference to the lives of people is immensely more satisfying than being the nth electrophysiologist in a hospital&amp;nbsp;abroad. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="electrophysiology"></category></entry><entry><title>Painting flowers with light</title><link href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/painting-with-light.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-03-29T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2015-03-29T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Raja Selvaraj</name></author><id>tag:rajaselvaraj.co.in,2015-03-29:/painting-with-light.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As a small weekend project, I shot a few indoor pictures with a somewhat new (to me) technique. What I …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As a small weekend project, I shot a few indoor pictures with a somewhat new (to me) technique. What I wanted was to show colorful flowers with a completely dark background. I didn&amp;#8217;t want to use a flash because the light would be too harsh, it reduces the &amp;#8220;depth&amp;#8221; in the picture and may illuminate the background because of its reach. So I used the light from a mobile phone display which was soft and weak enough to only illuminate closer objects. The pictures came out better than I had hoped&amp;nbsp;for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset' src='/images/flowers1.jpg' title='Flowers' width='720px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset right' src='/images/flowers2.jpg' title='More flowers' width='720px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here is a quick rundown of the technique I&amp;nbsp;used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sketch shows the basic set&amp;nbsp;up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset' src='/images/howto.jpg' title='Setting up' width='980px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Camera set up on a tripod for long&amp;nbsp;exposure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flowers set up on a stand in a dark&amp;nbsp;room&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A mobile phone display was used to provide the soft lighting during the&amp;nbsp;shoot. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any background objects are far off so that the light would not reach&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s it, set up a suitably long exposure. Focus in manual mode accurately with lights on. Then with lights off, trigger the shutter remotely if possible to avoid shake. During the exposure, use the glow from the phone display to light up the flowers. Move it around to light from all directions and avoid shadows. Review the picture, adjust shutter time as required to get the correct&amp;nbsp;exposure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listed below were my settings&amp;nbsp;-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Camera&lt;/strong&gt; - Canon &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EOS&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;550D &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lens&lt;/strong&gt;   -  Canon 50 mm&amp;nbsp;f1.8&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;    - 100,  Low &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ISO&lt;/span&gt; = less&amp;nbsp;noise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aperture&lt;/strong&gt; -  f/6.3, Gives enough depth of field to have all the flowers in&amp;nbsp;focus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exposure&lt;/strong&gt; - 20 seconds, Long exposure to capture the image in low light, also gives time to move the phone and illuminate the flowers&amp;nbsp;uniformly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="photography"></category></entry><entry><title>Walking in Wonderland - Trekking across the frozen Chadar</title><link href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/walking-in-wonderland.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-03-06T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2014-03-06T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Raja Selvaraj</name></author><id>tag:rajaselvaraj.co.in,2014-03-06:/walking-in-wonderland.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On no other trek could I have truthfully said that I was struck by a sense of wonder every time …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On no other trek could I have truthfully said that I was struck by a sense of wonder every time I looked up and around. We seemed to be walking and living in wonderland. It was much later, after seeing the reactions of others to the pictures that I realised that this was a near universal feeling, not something limited to me. Perhaps it was the simplicity of the landscape - ice, green waters, blue skies and brown&amp;nbsp;cliffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset left' src='/images/chadar_trek.jpg' title='Trekking on Chadar' width='400px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Couple of months ago, when we started planning to do the Chadar trek, with a sense of urgency imparted by news of a road that was coming up along the river, I had been a little worried that this simplicity of landscape might turn out to be monotonous. Thankfully, these turned out to have been unfounded and in the end, I was simply glad I&amp;nbsp;came.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Zanskar valley in the Himalayas is one of the most inaccessible inhabited places in the world. It is also one of the coldest inhabited places on earth, and in winter, with the snow and ice, all routes over land are closed and villages deep in the valley become isolated. For centuries these villagers have then used the frozen blanket of ice (chadar) over the Zanskar river to reach the rest of the world. The cold, along with the high walls of the valley that makes it difficult for sunlight to enter, ensures a good ice cover in winter. At present, the road from Leh reaches upto Chilling, leaving about 70 km of trekking over the frozen river before reaching the village at Nerak. Even as we trekked, the road was being extended further from Chilling, so there is a real chance of the romance of the trek being lost in a couple of years if there is road going all the&amp;nbsp;way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset left' src='/images/chadar_mist.jpg' title='Mist on the mountains' width='500px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Difficulty wise, there was conflicting advice before the trek. Obviously the temperature was the major concern. But looking back now, this was a moderate trek at most. It was never physically demanding and there were none of the altitude problems that plagued me on the Stok Kangri climb. Walking on the ice was an interesting experience. There is the legend of eskimos having a large number for snow. The varieties of ice we saw and became familiar with was a good illustration of how this might be true. With experience and a few falls we learned to recognize the glassy, smooth surfaced that posed the greatest risk of a slip and fall, the still smooth surfaced, but milky ice that had a better grip, ice with a brittle top layer that would crumble with pressure and provide good friction, and many more &amp;#8230; Slipping on the ice was unpredictable and not that funny, except for the people watching. But luckily for us, at the turn around point, Nerak, it snowed overnight. That transformed the whole route and the hitherto slippery ice became much easier to&amp;nbsp;negotiate. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photography was an interesting challenge. The landscape with crystal clear waters was picturesque and the open expanses were suited for wide angle lenses. However, one of the problems was the rarity of sunlight. The high valley walls meant that we saw the sun rarely even when the sky was clear. When light did come in, it was difficult to avoid the sharp shadows. The other problem was that the amount of white ice in most frames will fool the automatic exposure into underexposing the pictures. So, unless you intentionally &amp;#8216;overexpose&amp;#8217; the pictures, the landscape would come out dull grey. Despite the challenges, in the final reckoning, the pictures came out quite&amp;nbsp;well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset left' src='/images/chadar_landscape.jpg' title='Mist on the mountains' width='500px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset right' src='/images/frozen_falls.jpg' title='The frozen waterfall' width='400px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the best moments of the trek were when I was walking alone. Opportunities to do this were limited, due to the substantial number of groups trekking at the same time and the relative safety of staying together when walking on ice. On the last day of the return, I felt fresh and strong and pushed on at the front for most of the day until I ran out of steam at the end. But the more memorable moment was on the third day on one of the first occasions that I strayed from the pack. Among the curving segments of the river, I soon found myself quite alone with noone to see ahead of or behind me and was enjoying the solitude. And then I was dragged out of my reverie to notice that I could not make out any footprints of drag marks from the walking poles anywhere near me. I was somewhere near the middle of the river and the ice glistened pristine all around me without the reassuring footprints that would indicate that someone had safely walked here. The ice was sloping and smooth in front of me and looked too risky to walk across. On the side, it looked brittle. I stood there, wondering what to do and then there was a creeeak.. on one side as some ice cracked. As I stood absolutely still, there followed a creeeeak.. on the other side and I was having visions of the ice breaking all around and leaving me floating on a raft in hollywood style. Of course, I was able to retrace some steps safely and come around by a sturdier path, but that moment remains frozen in memory - standing alone in the middle of the frozen sheet with the groans of cracking ice all around, not daring to take a step in any&amp;nbsp;direction!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="trek"></category><category term="Himalayas"></category></entry><entry><title>Using wfdbtools</title><link href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/using-wfdbtools.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-06-15T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2013-06-15T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Raja Selvaraj</name></author><id>tag:rajaselvaraj.co.in,2013-06-15:/using-wfdbtools.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/RajaS/ecgtk/blob/master/ecgtk/wfdbtools.py"&gt;wfdbtools&lt;/a&gt; is a pure python module for accessing and using the waveform data in &lt;a href="http://www.physionet.org/physiobank/"&gt;Physiobank&lt;/a&gt;. Provides rdsamp and rdann which …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/RajaS/ecgtk/blob/master/ecgtk/wfdbtools.py"&gt;wfdbtools&lt;/a&gt; is a pure python module for accessing and using the waveform data in &lt;a href="http://www.physionet.org/physiobank/"&gt;Physiobank&lt;/a&gt;. Provides rdsamp and rdann which are the python equivalents of the wfdb applications of similar names. A deliberate attempt is made to try to keep names and usage similar to the original wfdb applications for simplicity of&amp;nbsp;use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only dependency that will need to be installed is numpy. However, to use the function plot_data, which is an utility function for interactive use, you need to have matplotlib also&amp;nbsp;installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example&amp;nbsp;Usage:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;wfdbtools&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;rdsamp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;rdann&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;plot_data&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;pprint&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;pprint&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Record is a format 212 record from physiobank.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Note that name of record does not include extension.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;record&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;samples/format212/100&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Read in the data from 0 to 10 seconds&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;info&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;rdsamp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;record&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# returned data is an array. The columns are time(samples),&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# time(seconds), signal1, signal2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;shape&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3600&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# info is a dictionary containing header information&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;pprint&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;info&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;first_values&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;995&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1011&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;gains&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;200&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;200&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;samp_count&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;650000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;samp_freq&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;360&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;signal_names&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;MLII&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;V5&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;zero_values&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1024&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1024&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# And now read the annotation&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;ann&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;rdann&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;record&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;atr&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# ann has 3 columns - sample number, time (sec) and annotation code&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ann&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,:])&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;array&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;([[&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="mf"&gt;18.&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.05&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class="mf"&gt;28.&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;
           &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="mf"&gt;77.&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.214&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class="mf"&gt;1.&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;370.&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class="mf"&gt;1.028&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class="mf"&gt;1.&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;
           &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;662.&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class="mf"&gt;1.839&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class="mf"&gt;1.&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;span class="p"&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Plot the data and the mark the annotations&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;plot_data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;info&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ann&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset center' src='/images/wfdb_plot.png' title='Plot' width='600px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="python"></category><category term="linux"></category><category term="ecg"></category></entry><entry><title>Kurangani to Top Station trek Sep 2012</title><link href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/kurangani-to-top-station-trek.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-10-25T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2012-10-25T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Raja Selvaraj</name></author><id>tag:rajaselvaraj.co.in,2012-10-25:/kurangani-to-top-station-trek.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset left' src='/images/sliding_down.png' title='Sliding down' width='500px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The promised easy route down from Top Station was slowly turning nightmarish. For more than two hours we were following …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset left' src='/images/sliding_down.png' title='Sliding down' width='500px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The promised easy route down from Top Station was slowly turning nightmarish. For more than two hours we were following our guides through dense forest, with no trail, pushing away thorns, trying unsuccessfully to avoid the stinging nettles, repeatedly getting feet entangled in vine that proved much stronger than it looked, as we slid down the slopes and somehow managed to negotiate our way across a steep slope with sparse footholds, a slip from which would have plunged us onto the rocky walls of a stream far below. We were catching our breath in a clearing when the guide casually mentioned that the dead rotting leaves all around us could harbour king cobras. Some how, at that moment, with everything else, it did not seem to&amp;nbsp;matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our trek started on a friday night, travelling by car from Chennai, to the village of Kurangani via Trichy, Dindigul, Theni and Bodi. This village formed the &amp;#8220;bottom station&amp;#8221; for a ropeway that extended to &amp;#8220;central station&amp;#8221; and further on to &amp;#8220;top station&amp;#8221;, that was used to bring down the tea from Munnar to the plains by the British. The villagers told us it would take about 3 hours to Central Station and another 2-3 hours to Top Station. It was almost 10 in the morning, but we assured them we were seasoned trekkers and it would be easy for us to reach the top by evening. We set off, and within half an hour, the slope and the heat left us&amp;nbsp;panting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset right' src='/images/on_the_way.jpg' title='On the way' width='460px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we reached a waterfall on the way, we took a break without any hesitation to enjoy a dip in the cool waters. We ended up spending an hour here before we took off again to battle the climb and the terrible heat. There was poor cover over the trail leaving us fully exposed to the fierce heat of the sun. About 3 hours later, we reached Central Station for a late lunch. Stuffed with the tasty meal cooked by a local villager and with a couple of glasses of lemonade each from the village store, we decided to rest and move to Top Station the next day. We enjoyed a relaxed evening, with a small walk at sunset and an early&amp;nbsp;bedtime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset right' src='/images/day2.png' title='On the way' width='460px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sunday morning found us back on the trail by 6.30 am and we were able to beat the heat to reach the top by 9.30 am. Apart from a few buildings in ruins and a large platform at top station, there was very little evidence of the existence of the ropeway along the whole route. At top station, we decided to take a guided walk in Pambadum sanctuary. The forest department officials seemed grumpy that we had disturbed their session of morning paper reading and small talk, but finally we set off with a guide on a picturesque walk. Here we also saw the remnants of the &amp;#8216;escape route&amp;#8217; the disused road to kodaikanal. We had lunch and then a local offered to assist us in finding a good campsite. This place was out of the main Top Station area, took a full hour&amp;#8217;s walk to get to, and was on the hillside, opposite the view point on Top Station and overlooking the&amp;nbsp;plains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset left' src='/images/campside_night.png' title='Campside at night' width='430px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We set up the tent and spent a pleasant hour sitting on chairs in the fading daylight, talking. By now, we had three people &amp;#8220;helping&amp;#8221; us, one the caretaker of the place and the others the locals who had brought us here. They promised to give us soup in the evening, and dinner with chapathis and eggs. Not having change, I gave them a 500 rupee note to cover the expected expenses of about Rs.200. To our surprise all three disappeared to buy the groceries and while the hours passed and darkness fell, there was no sign of the three. When they returned after a couple of hours, it was with the smell of alcohol on their breath and a bill for about 5 times the initially expected amount. Alone at night on a lonely hillside, there wasn&amp;#8217;t much we could do about this and a lot of pestering for a bill resulted in one being produced next morning where the numbers were clearly altered to inflate the total. There was nothing to do, but take it as part of the adventure. To their credit they could be persuaded to accompany us on the way down on the previously described hair-raising non-trail. This finally led to a lovely waterfall in dense forest where we had a refreshing bath. After some unpleasant moments of haggling over their payment, we finally set off on a winding climb down in a lovely&amp;nbsp;landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset right' src='/images/picturesque_return.png' title='Picturesque return' width='460px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A steep climb down brought us to a small settlement, from where we walked in the hot midday sun to finally reach Kurangani again. Back on the road, and we were home by&amp;nbsp;midnight. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="trek"></category><category term="south india"></category></entry><entry><title>A month with Sublime Text</title><link href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/a-month-with-sublime-text.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-07-31T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2012-07-31T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Raja Selvaraj</name></author><id>tag:rajaselvaraj.co.in,2012-07-31:/a-month-with-sublime-text.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset center' src='/images/ST_screenshot.png' title='Sublime Text 2' width='600px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t write code for a living, still the amount of time I spend doing it makes me value …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset center' src='/images/ST_screenshot.png' title='Sublime Text 2' width='600px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t write code for a living, still the amount of time I spend doing it makes me value a good editor. Like any decent programmer I am picky about what I use and biased towards what I prefer. Over the years, I have tried out a few different editors, notably gedit, geany, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SPE&lt;/span&gt;, Komodo edit, Vim and Emacs. With patience and persistence, I think anyone will ultimately find the answer in Vi(m) or Emacs. For me it was Emacs that clicked and since the last 4 years or so, I have not really felt the need to try out another editor. With all the noise about Sublime Text, I thought it was time to give it a whirl, especially with the release of version 2, especially since some of the things in my current emacs setup were broken after the upgrade to Emacs 24. I used Sublime Text for about a month and these are some of my impressions -
&lt;!-- more --&gt;
  1. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ST&lt;/span&gt; is blazing fast. With about 10 open files, it still restarts virtually instantaneously, while Emacs, even with my core i7 processor and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSD&lt;/span&gt;, takes a few seconds to start up. Practically though, this is not of much importance, since with my usual workflow, Emacs is always open and I wait for it to start up only once in a month or so when I reboot after a kernel&amp;nbsp;upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It comes with batteries included! With the default install, it is nice to see most things work automatically. In python mode for example, indentation, autocompletion, code folding all work out of the box. Once the package manager is installed, it is very easy to find and install additional packages. Although Emacs diehards usually discount the usefulness of folding, I found it quite useful and it is absolutely effortless in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ST&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The enthusiasm of the author and the community for new developments in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ST&lt;/span&gt; is infectious and even if the intermittent popups reminding you that is a trial are a little irritating, it is an incredibly good decision to allow a free trial without time limit to attract new&amp;nbsp;users. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming from Emacs, the thing that I had the biggest difficulty in adjusting to was with creating a new file. The process in Emacs is a good example of the smooth workflow that has evolved with time. Creating a new file is the same as opening a file. If the parent directory does not exist, Emacs still creates the file and opens the buffer with a warning that you have to create the parent directory. And on M-x make-directory, the path for the parent directory is automatically filled in, so all you have to do is press enter. Compared to this &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ST&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s traditional method of &amp;#8216;Create file&amp;#8217; followed by &amp;#8216;Save&amp;#8217; seems&amp;nbsp;cumbersome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could not get syntax highlighting to work with Markdown mode in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ST&lt;/span&gt;. Other people have reported this and suggest that this is a problem with certain themes, but there was no change for me with different&amp;nbsp;themes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Emacs can use a file dialog, the default method to display files for opening or saving is in the minibuffer. Again, having got used to this, dialogs seem so much out of place, but I could not find any plugin to get ido like behaviour for opening files in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ST&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Macros are a very powerful feature of Emacs and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ST&lt;/span&gt; has them too. Or is supposed to have them too. While I did not have problems with a few simple macros, most of those I tried did not work as expected. I did not spend much time trying to debug, but it is likely that the keybindings introduced by Sublemacspro may have been responsible. But again, with Emacs, macros have never gone wrong, no matter what keybindings have been&amp;nbsp;changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self documentation is another powerful feature of Emacs. For example, &amp;#8216;C-h k&amp;#8217; for &amp;#8216;describe key&amp;#8217; will bring up the function currently bound to that key. I sorely missed something like that in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ST&lt;/span&gt;. Key bindings in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ST&lt;/span&gt; are defined in multiple places, so again it was not easy to find the current binding for a key combination. This also makes it more difficult customizing &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ST&lt;/span&gt; compared to Emacs where you can put all your customizations in one file or a few files as you&amp;nbsp;wish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The killer feature that forced me to return to Emacs is org-mode. I am not a power user of org-mode, far from it. But still I use it to store a few notes and I found my self opening Emacs just to use my org files. There seems to be some preliminary effort to make an org-mode clone in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ST&lt;/span&gt;, but there is nothing functional&amp;nbsp;yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, it was a good experience and it was with somewhat mixed feelings that I returned to Emacs. I have subsequently tweaked my Emacs to get some of the features I missed after leaving &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ST&lt;/span&gt;. My general impression is that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ST&lt;/span&gt; seems to principally cater for those coming from Textmate. For Vim users, it might again be a reasonable switch as it seems to have good support of Vi keybindings. Emacs bindings are provided by a package and are still not perfect. For now, I am comfortably back in Emacs, but might try &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ST&lt;/span&gt; again after some time. A month has been too short a time to evaluate an editor and I have not tried any serious&amp;nbsp;customization. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="editor"></category><category term="linux"></category></entry><entry><title>Hotkey to toggle touchpad on Thinkpad x220</title><link href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/hotkey-to-toggle-touchpad-on-thinkpad-x220.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-05-31T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2012-05-31T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Raja Selvaraj</name></author><id>tag:rajaselvaraj.co.in,2012-05-31:/hotkey-to-toggle-touchpad-on-thinkpad-x220.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My thinkpad x220 is my third thinkpad and the first one with a touchpad. While I find it useful specifically …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My thinkpad x220 is my third thinkpad and the first one with a touchpad. While I find it useful specifically for scrolling documents and for zooming in and out for images, it can also come in the way the rest of the time hen I am primarily using the keyboard and trackpoint. So I wanted to be able to toggle the touchpad on and off using a key.
&lt;!-- more --&gt;
xinput gave me the following output, so I know the id for my touchpad is&amp;nbsp;11.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;⎡ Virtual core pointer                      id=2    [master pointer  (3)]
⎜   ↳ Virtual core XTEST pointer                id=4    [slave  pointer  (2)]
⎜   ↳ TPPS/2 IBM TrackPoint                     id=13   [slave  pointer  (2)]
⎜   ↳ SynPS/2 Synaptics TouchPad                id=11   [slave  pointer  (2)]
⎣ Virtual core keyboard                     id=3    [master keyboard (2)]
    ↳ Virtual core XTEST keyboard               id=5    [slave  keyboard (3)]
    ↳ Power Button                              id=6    [slave  keyboard (3)]
    ↳ Video Bus                                 id=7    [slave  keyboard (3)]
    ↳ Sleep Button                              id=8    [slave  keyboard (3)]
    ↳ Integrated Camera                         id=9    [slave  keyboard (3)]
    ↳ AT Translated Set 2 keyboard              id=10   [slave  keyboard (3)]
    ↳ ThinkPad Extra Buttons                    id=12   [slave  keyboard (3)]
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then starting from &lt;a href="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/SynapticsTouchpad/ShortcutKey"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, I wrote the following simple&amp;nbsp;script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; #!/bin/sh

 # I know my trackpad device id is 11
 tp_enabled=`xinput list-props 11 | grep &amp;quot;Device Enabled&amp;quot; | awk &amp;#39;{print $4}&amp;#39;`

 # if enabled, disable it
 if [ $tp_enabled = 1 ]
 then
     xinput set-prop 11 &amp;quot;Device Enabled&amp;quot; 0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; notify-send &amp;#39;Trackpad disabled&amp;#39;

 # if disabled, enable it
 elif [ $tp_enabled = 0 ]
 then
     xinput set-prop 11 &amp;quot;Device Enabled&amp;quot; 1 &amp;amp;&amp;amp; notify-send &amp;#39;Trackpad enabled&amp;#39;

 else
 notify-send &amp;#39;Could not get trackpad status&amp;#39;
 fi
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset right' src='/images/toggle_trackpad_screenshot.png' title='screenshot' width='600px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on whether the touchpad is enabled or not (getting it from &amp;#8216;xinput list-props 11&amp;#8217;), the script accordingly turns it on or off, by using &amp;#8216;xinput set-prop&amp;#8217;. In addition a notification appears through notify-osd. I put this script in my path, made it executable and then bound it to F5 (System Settings -&amp;gt; Keyboard -&amp;gt; Shortcuts -&amp;gt; Custom shortcuts). It works perfectly, with the only issue being that the norification bubble stays for 10 seconds and although the man page for notify-send lists the argument &amp;#8212;expire-time, this does not work. This apparently is a long-standing bug/feature(?) and I didn&amp;#8217;t want to &lt;a href="http://askubuntu.com/questions/128474/how-to-customize-on-screen-notifications"&gt;go to some lengths&lt;/a&gt; at present to work around&amp;nbsp;this.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="linux"></category><category term="thinkpad"></category></entry><entry><title>Install Mendeley plugin for Libreoffice</title><link href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/install-mendeley-plugin-for-libreoffice.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-05-25T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2012-05-25T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Raja Selvaraj</name></author><id>tag:rajaselvaraj.co.in,2012-05-25:/install-mendeley-plugin-for-libreoffice.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;, I struggled with this for half an hour, so just to document the solution. On my new laptop with …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;, I struggled with this for half an hour, so just to document the solution. On my new laptop with Ubuntu 12.04 and Libreoffice 3.5, I installed &lt;a href="http://www.mendeley.com/"&gt;Mendeley&lt;/a&gt; with the deb package from the website. Installation went well, but when trying to install the openoffice plugin, it first complained it could not find unopkg. After some time I found that this was now located at /usr/lib/libreoffice/program/. So I pointed Mendeleydesktop towards this and now it ended with a warning that &amp;#8216;Couldn&amp;#8217;t Install OpenOffice Plugin The OpenOffice unopkg utility gave the following output:&amp;#8217;. I read about manually installing the oxt which is at &amp;#8216;/opt/mendeleydesktop/share/mendeleydesktop/openOfficePlugin/Mendeley-1.5.2.oxt&amp;#8217; and opened the extension manager at libreoffice when I found that the Mendeley plugin is already installed. So, all I had to was restart Libreoffice and the Mendeley toolbar was now&amp;nbsp;available.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="linux"></category></entry><entry><title>Bali Pass via Dehradun May 2012</title><link href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/bali-pass-via-dehradun.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-05-24T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2012-05-24T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Raja Selvaraj</name></author><id>tag:rajaselvaraj.co.in,2012-05-24:/bali-pass-via-dehradun.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I had my life to live over&amp;#8230; &lt;br&gt;
I would go more places. &lt;br&gt;
I would climb more mountains and swim …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I had my life to live over&amp;#8230; &lt;br&gt;
I would go more places. &lt;br&gt;
I would climb more mountains and swim more rivers&amp;#8230; &lt;br&gt;
- Don&amp;nbsp;Harold&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset left' src='/images/IMG_2767.JPG' title='Trek to Bali pass' width='300px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After months of deliberation and planning, we had decided on the trek to Bali pass in May 2012 with 14 signing up. The plan was to reach Dehradun and then drive on to the end of the road at Taluka. From here we would walk, climb the pass whose highest point was at 4800 m, descend on the other side and reach road again at Janaki Chatti from where we would drive back to Dehradun. For 4 of us, this would be the third trek in the Himalayas together, starting with Hampta pass in September 2010. Another 7 would be enjoying their second trek with us and the other 3 were new faces. The group was drawn from a wide range of places from New York and Singapore to Delhi, Pune and Chennai. Finally, the day we had planned for, had waited for eagerly, was there &amp;#8230;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;May&amp;nbsp;02&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Five of us flew out of Chennai late evening to reach Delhi close to midnight. We went over to a friend&amp;#8217;s place for a mini party, eating chaats, dhokla, chicken kababs and other assorted stuff. The hosts seemed to be running around all night refilling plates and glasses, cleaning up and setting up makeshift beds while we shamefully just ate, drank and slept. As I nodded off, I was thinking I would never do this for anyone at my home, not even if they were my ten best&amp;nbsp;friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;May&amp;nbsp;03&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset left' src='/images/IMG_1959.JPG' title='On the road' width='200px' /&gt;
In the New Delhi railway station, the whole team came together and we boarded the Shatabdi. We were served at regular intervals with coffee, snacks or breakfast and rolled into Dehradun on time at noon. Here we met our guides for the trip, Jayanth a.k.a Mowgli and Ashish from &lt;a href="http://www.facebook.com/pages/The-Himalayan-Wanderers/218075611589062"&gt;Himalayan Wanderers&lt;/a&gt; and were taken to a hotel close to the railway station for a simple vegetarian lunch. We left by 2.00 pm on two cars. A long, somewhat cramped, often picturesque and occasionally scary ride brought us to Sankri by about 9 pm. The last hour or so to Taluka over a bad road was thus done in darkness. At Taluka, we slept well, knowing we wouldnt be sleeping on a soft bed for a few days&amp;nbsp;now. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;May&amp;nbsp;04&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First day of the trek. After the drive, it felt good to get going on your feet. All the way, we walked along the river Tons through some lush forests. It is a gentle climb for most of the way with a couple of segments that go down. We cover a distance of about 13 km going up from an altitude of 1900 m to 2560 m. Osla is a small village and we camped in two man tents. I slept poorly, having difficulty adjusting to a tent and sleeping&amp;nbsp;bag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset left' src='/images/IMG_2036.JPG' title='The forested trail' width='400px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;May&amp;nbsp;05&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset left' src='/images/IMG_2169.JPG' title='The long climb' width='400px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second day&amp;#8217;s trek was quite a warm up, a 10 hour climb from Osla to Har Ki Dun at an altitude of 3566 m. We crossed the river and had a steady, stiff climb ahead of us for most of the way. It was a climb with sparse vegetation and a rocky path, but with a lovely waterfalls on the way to break the monotony. Before sunset we had a few moments to enjoy a view of the Har Ki Doon valley before returning to our beautiful campsite for the day, near a stream. Tonight I again slept badly and it would be another night before I made peace with the sleeping&amp;nbsp;bag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;May&amp;nbsp;06&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After our detour to Har Ki Doon, we retraced most of the route today, which meant a steep climb down, taxing everyone&amp;#8217;s knees. There was a little excitement for a while when we noticed Sanjeev was missing, but it turned out that he had gone ahead by a different trail. Original plan was to reach Debshu Bugyal, but we stopped a little ahead of it to give us some time for &amp;#8216;adventure activities&amp;#8217;. Our guides set up ropes for a river crossing which was exhilirating and then we learnt some rock climbing on a small rock before setting up&amp;nbsp;camp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset left' src='/images/IMG_2423.JPG' title='River crossing' width='420px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;May&amp;nbsp;07&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up until this point, we had mules carrying all the stuff, but we were due to change to porters today. Unfortunately we found that the porters who were to have reported this morning failed to turn up and so we had to find fresh porters from the village. All this meant we were still sitting around at 10 am unable to get going. Finally, with news of some porters arriving in a few hours, we decided to cover some ground at least with some of us carrying our own bags. We trekked for 3-4 hours with an initial steep climb to Debshu Bugyal, then coming down a short steep slope and going on a little more to reach a lovely campsite by a stream for a late lunch. We had an expanse of riverbed that had soft sand cluttered with pebbles and larger stones. With the sun and a clear sky this was like a lovely summer day at the beach and we enjoyed a beach-side lunch. With most of the day left, we spent time playing &amp;#8216;dog and the bone&amp;#8217; and later on, handball with a ball made of rolled up socks! In between someone came up with the idea of taking in a dip in the stream. Tentatively putting my leg in, I was able to bear the freezing water for only 30 seconds. So I changed and went in with no little apprehension, but once in, it turned out be fun and an impromptu challenge with Sushanth went into a deadlock for more than a minute only broken by us coming out together. Late evening we had a campfire, and despite missing some meat to barbeque in the campfire, we had fun trading stories.
&lt;img class='inset left' src='/images/IMG_2514.JPG' title='Handball' width='400px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;May&amp;nbsp;08&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having had a free day, the plan today was to push it to the base of Bali pass. In between, we intended to visit Ruinsara Tal before crossing the river on a bridge. We had to walk on a trail on the steep sides of a stream. Turned out that the rains in the last couple of weeks had left a series of landslides all along the trail and now we found the trail broken at maybe 10 places by these slides. We had to find our way above, under or across these places, trusting our feet to hold on to the steep, loose sides, hoping that neither our feet nor the trail would give way to send us sliding down to the stream below. It was a long and tough walk, a steady climb of about 16 km to reach the Tal at 3500 m. When we reached the area tired and late in evening, we found that the bridge that we had planned to use to cross the stream was broken. In addition, there was a brief hailstorm with thunder raising concerns about the weather on the pass. Unable to cross over to the base of the pass, we camped near the Tal, which by the way was a small but delightful high altitude&amp;nbsp;lake. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset left' src='/images/IMG_2608.JPG' title='Another landslide to cross' width='400px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;May&amp;nbsp;09&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite much coaxing, the porters refused to cross the stream or climb up to the pass. There seemed to be nothing to do but change plans to reach the pass and return to camp today. This would also give some rest to three indisposed trekkers who elected to stay behind at camp. We started off at about 6.30 am, at least an hour too late in retrospect. We had a short descent down to the stream and the first task was to cross the stream. While two of the &amp;#8216;streamlets&amp;#8217; could be crossed over logs or stones without stepping into the water, there was no getting around this for one of the wider sections. Wading through absolutely freezing water with bare feet and dancing once on the other side to get some sensation back into the feet is not something any of us would forget soon! Once across, we put on gaiters along with the shoes since we were now entering snow country.&lt;img class='inset right' src='/images/IMG_2793.JPG' title='Climbing to the pass' width='450px' /&gt;
After an initial steep climb, we started walking along a gentle incline towards the foot of the pass. This was apparently unseasonal amount of snow with the locals not having seeing this much snow at this time of the year for 20 years. By the time we reached the base of the pass, we were walking all the time in snow. Trudging in snow in which we kept sinking till the knees now, while all the time climbing and climbing turned out to be much harder than we would have imagined. Three of the 11 who left camp decided to stop in between while there were still some rocks to stay put. The other 8 of us were stretched out in a long line with me closer to the end. We soon ran out of places to sit even and had no option but to keep walking. By now, all of us had also run out of water (another mistake, with hindsight; we should have carried more water) and had our bottles filled with snow. Adding to the misery, my left gaiter strap broke and snow started seeping inside the shoes, slowly freezing my feet. At 12.30 pm, we stopped to rest, sitting down in the snow itself. The highest point of the pass seemed deceptively close, maybe only a few hundred metres away, but there was still a fair bit to climb and judging from our speed so far, we knew it would take almost 2 hours. At that point, we did not have the time to do this and get back safely in time. So, reluctantly, we had to turn back. Just as we reached the base of the pass on the way back, hail started to fall again and we saw a couple of small&amp;nbsp;avalanches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;May&amp;nbsp;10&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today we began our return trip, walking back to Debshu Bugyal and on to Osla. Mostly downhill with some stretches where we had to climb. It was not too taxing at any point, although it seemed to me that we crossed the landslide areas with less care than we did in the other direction and it got scary for me at least in some places. One week of camp cooking had left everyone hankering for things to eat. On the way to Osla we stopped at a small shop to have Maggi and then at Osla itself, we had some scrambled eggs. This would also be our last night in tents. I had by now got used to the tent routine and knew I would miss&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;May&amp;nbsp;11&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I woke up pretty early and went out to shoot some birds (with the camera, of course). We had a relatively easy walk ahead of us, but returning by the same route always seems much less fun than walking on a route for the first time. We reached Taluka in the evening and had more eggs (omelette!). We had a post trek celebration with chicken and drinks, with toasts for everyone. Although Taluka is a small place without electricity or phone signal, it was civilization alright. So it was back to the life of Barbarians for us, with chicken, soft beds and bathrooms (yikes!). Tomorrow the phones will start ringing and life will never be the same&amp;nbsp;again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;May&amp;nbsp;12&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started at about 9 am on what turned out to be a 11 hour drive to Dehradun, dashing hopes for a bath at Dehradun. We just had enough time for dinner and a dash to the station to catch an overnight train to&amp;nbsp;Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;May&amp;nbsp;13&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;End of the trek early morning at Delhi as people split up. It seemed to be hot and dusty and we felt exhausted suddenly, agreeing this was low altitude sickness! This was my third trip to the Himalayas and was arguably the one I enjoyed the most. From the stark beauty of the snow fields to the enchanting loveliness of the forests, we saw it all. The organisers did an amazing&amp;nbsp;job. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally my trekmates were the best I could have got. Nagi was the life of the trek, provided inspiration for all the younger trekkers on the trails and dispensed wisdom to the villagers in our nightly rounds of &lt;a href="http://www.eblong.com/zarf/werewolf.html"&gt;The villagers and the werewolves&lt;/a&gt;. On the other end of the age spectrum, Arun who had struggled alongside me on the first trek, now nonchalantly strode in the front everyday carrying his rucksack, becoming an inspiration himself. Sushanth justified the efforts I had put in from the beginning to make sure he would be on the team by demonstrating his fighting spirit and the showdown we had in the freezing waters was, for me, the most memorable moment of the trip. 
&lt;img class='inset left' src='/images/chalenge.jpg' title='Most memorable' width='650px' /&gt;
Siva, as usual, was what noone else can be, with his innovative methods for luring vultures and impromptu flute recitals. Belying the initial impression that he had not changed much since his marriage, Vishravars finally gace proof of the improvement by not losing a single item on the trek. Ragou earned everyone&amp;#8217;s respect for battling it each day despite the excruciating pain in his knees and then still being able to walk into camp with a smile at the end of the day. Priya endeared herself to everyone when she proved herself guileless enough to not be able to deny that she was a werewolf. Viji showed a lot of &amp;#8216;American&amp;#8217; aggressiveness and intensity in all the games which was sometimes daunting, but Viji, I cannot forget your touching faith in me, defending me from the irate villagers throughout that round in the game while I gobbled them up every night. Bhavani, as we have come to know him, was the silent man, always in the background, but somehow evoking confidence that were you to fall into the river, he would be the first guy to jump in to save you. Anu was the kid of the group, trotting along with her small bag and was her endearing self for most of the trek and then exasperatingly, would get upset over the smallest thing and drive people crazy. &lt;img class='inset right' src='/images/fab14.jpg' title='The team' width='500px' /&gt; It was incredible how Durga could always do so much while appearing to do so little and show so little strain, but what I won&amp;#8217;t forget easily is how you played host on the first day. Finally, my good friend Sudhakar has always been my guide from the day we started making the plans and no trek will be complete without his entertaining&amp;nbsp;stories. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is to more mountains in the future&amp;nbsp;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/photos/110096133793307529650/albums/5744237625668484641"&gt;More&amp;nbsp;pictures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="trek"></category><category term="Himalayas"></category></entry><entry><title>Textcontrol with smart autocompletion for wxpython</title><link href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/textcontrol-with-smart-autocompletion-for-wxpython.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-05-23T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2012-05-23T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Raja Selvaraj</name></author><id>tag:rajaselvaraj.co.in,2012-05-23:/textcontrol-with-smart-autocompletion-for-wxpython.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For my own use I needed a text entry widget in wxpython that allows smart autocompletion from a list of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For my own use I needed a text entry widget in wxpython that allows smart autocompletion from a list of choices. By smart autocompletion, I mean choices should be displayed in a dropdown box and text entry should narrow down to matching choices. Match should be configurable to beginning only or anywhere within the string. Starting off from &lt;a href="http://wiki.wxpython.org/TextCtrlAutoComplete"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, I wrote my own textcontrol widget with autocomplete. A list of choices can be passed to the widget and matches can be configured. Check it out on &lt;a href="https://github.com/RajaS/ACTextCtrl"&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset left' src='/images/actextctrl_screenshot.png' title='Autocomplete in action' width='600px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="python"></category><category term="wxpython"></category></entry><entry><title>Linux on Thinkpad x220</title><link href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/linux-on-thinkpad.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-05-18T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2012-05-18T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Raja Selvaraj</name></author><id>tag:rajaselvaraj.co.in,2012-05-18:/linux-on-thinkpad.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I bought a Lenovo Thinkpad X 220 recently. This is my third thinkpad, the previous ones being an X40 (stolen …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I bought a Lenovo Thinkpad X 220 recently. This is my third thinkpad, the previous ones being an X40 (stolen) and an X61s (showing signs of wear and tear after 4 years of heavy use). Overall, there is nothing to disappoint a thinkpad fan with the fantastic keyboard and solid build as expected. The differences are a wider screen (mixed feeling about this, the width makes it easier to code with a split screen, but the loss of height needs some getting used to), a trackpad (which I don&amp;#8217;t use much) and some additional media buttons (again, not important for me). The screen is thinner and lighter and along with an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSD&lt;/span&gt; makes the system lighter.
&lt;!-- more --&gt;
The system came with Windows 7 preinstalled (there is no option to avoid the &amp;#8220;Windows tax&amp;#8221;). The last thinkpad I got, I had no second thoughts about removing Windows Vista and installing Linux. This time, however, I decided to try and retain Windows 7. I did not want to dual boot since I use Windows rarely. For virtualization, the options were to retain windows on the disk and use it in &amp;#8216;raw&amp;#8217; mode or to convert the physical windows partitions into a virtual disk. For the latter there seemed to be two solutions, &lt;a href="http://www.vmware.com/products/converter/"&gt;VMware&amp;#8217;s converter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/sysinternals/ee656415.aspx"&gt;Microsoft&amp;#8217;s disk2vhd&lt;/a&gt;.
disk2vhd was straightforward to use, working from within the running system itself. I selected all 3 partitions to make the virtual disk. This booted up fine in Virtualbox once virtualisation was enabled in the bios and the option &amp;#8216;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;IO&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;APIC&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217; was enabled in virtualbox.
I copied out the virtual hard disk and erased all the partitions before installing Ubuntu 12.04. As I have come to expect, the install was smooth and everything worked perfectly. With the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSD&lt;/span&gt;, booting up and resume from suspend are very fast and the system is very responsive and running cooler than my old&amp;nbsp;one. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="thinkpad"></category><category term="linux"></category></entry><entry><title>Kumbakarai to Kodaikanal - March 2012</title><link href="http://rajaselvaraj.co.in/kumbakarai-to-kodaikanal.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-03-27T10:20:00+05:30</published><updated>2012-03-27T10:20:00+05:30</updated><author><name>Raja Selvaraj</name></author><id>tag:rajaselvaraj.co.in,2012-03-27:/kumbakarai-to-kodaikanal.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset right' src='/images/on_the_way.jpg' title='On the way' width='400px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a decision made over just a couple of days. A weekend trek to help prepare for the big …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset right' src='/images/on_the_way.jpg' title='On the way' width='400px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a decision made over just a couple of days. A weekend trek to help prepare for the big one in the Himalayas that lay ahead in May. We learnt about this route from Kumbakarai falls to Kodaikanal which seemed to be &lt;a href="http://duraithelegaleagle.blogspot.in/2011/05/historic-kumbakarai-vellagavi.html"&gt;relatively well documented&lt;/a&gt; and decided on it. Prasanna, Vishravars and Arun drove from Chennai and picked me up in Tindivanam. After a dinner of tasty idlis at Prasanna&amp;#8217;s place, we proceeded towards Dindigul. From Dindigul, we traveled to Periakulam and on towards the falls. Some distance before entering the Kumbakarai main road, we decided to catch some sleep by the roadside. Lying down at 3.30 am under a tree near a temple, it seemed idyllic until a squadron of marauding mosquitoes found us. We managed to sleep a little by crawling into the sleeping bags. We were back on the road at 5.30, had some idlis (again!) in Kumbakarai and were at the falls by 7.30&amp;nbsp;am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset left' src='/images/starting_ff.jpg' title='Starting off' width='400px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started climbing at about 7.45 am and &lt;a href="http://nagaxvasanth.blogspot.in/2010/01/kumbakarai-vellagavi-vattakanal.html"&gt;this blog&lt;/a&gt; was very helpful with finding the right path in the first part. After that it is pretty much a straight trail that is easy to follow. We reached Vannathi Odai in about 30 minutes and were expecting some water, but it turned out to be bone dry. From here on, the trail was pretty steep and it was fairly hot too. Because of the conflicting information about the difficulty of the trek and the time needed to cross the trail, we had come fully prepared with sleeping bags, mats and so on. This added to the heat and the steepness to make it very tiring. By about 10 am, we lay down in a small clearing for a 45 minute rest. From here Vellagavi turned out to be almost 2 hours climb in hot sun up a steep&amp;nbsp;gradient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset left' src='/images/view_from_above.jpg' title='View from above' width='400px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vellagavi turned out to be a small, charming village where we had lunch and lay down for another rest. Vish woke up after a nightmare of getting lost in mist and wanted us to hurry on. We started off at 2.30 pm and continued climbing.
&lt;img class='inset right' src='/images/flowers.jpg' title='Flowers' width='250px' /&gt;
The heat did not abate even though we were higher now. About 5.30 we reached the Dolphin Nose point (Vattakanal). It turned out to be a little bit of an anticlimax as there was a further hour&amp;#8217;s walk across a path criss crossed with roots before we got to the road. Once in Vattakanale, we stopped at a cottage where the owner also got us hot water for everyone to bathe and a fantastic hot dinner of chapatthis with chicken. After the hot day&amp;#8217;s climb, Thattakanal was surprisingly cold in the night, but we were all exhausted and slept well under warm&amp;nbsp;blankets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class='inset left' src='/images/path_at_vattakanal.jpg' title='Path at Vattakanal' width='350px' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day, we started by about 7.30 am on the descent. It took 5 hours of steep climbing down to return to Kumbakarai. The chilled water in the pools was perfect after the hot day and we soaked for a few minutes before starting the drive back. All in all, this turned out to be a good, tough trek. My own impression is that this is a trek that is better done in Jan or Feb - it was already too hot and dry in March. If you are a fairly regular trekker, it is very much possible to climb up to the top in about 8-10 hours, so it is worth taking a light backpack and starting early.
&lt;img class='inset left' src='/images/black_eagle.jpg' title='Black Eagle' width='250px' /&gt;
For beginners, staying at Vellagavi is an option - this should take about 5 hours from Kumbakarai, so one can start a little later too. It seems extremely unlikely one would encounter wild animals besides such a well used trail. We heard no stories from the villagers either about any encounters with bears or gaur on the trail. There is a fair amount of birdlife along the way - mostly bulbuls and drongos, some bee-eaters and a few other species. You can read the &lt;a href="http://vishravars.blogspot.in/2012/03/kumbakarai-to-kodaikanal-and-back.html"&gt;account&lt;/a&gt; by Vish, one of my trekmates, for another view of the&amp;nbsp;trek.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="trek"></category></entry></feed>